A Guide to the Papers of the Barney, Cooke, McClew and Neilson families, 1820-1905
Special Collections Department, University of Virginia Library
- II. LETTERS FROM LAURA E. COOKE TO CHARLES BARNEY
  - Laura E. Cooke to Charles D. Barney [1872] Sep 28
    Sandusky, Ohio: Sallie's uncomfortable condition; funeral of Burton Spencer's wife; Jay [Cooke, Jr.] and Mollie; went to the Fair grounds; saw Lizzie Moss and husband Jay Butler, the Libby Hubbards, and Julia Radcliffe Cogswell; activities of their daughter Dolly; tea at Aunt Mary Cooke's; visit to the Farm; Aunt Selina Milliman and daughters Grace and Fanny visiting; baby Bessie needing to be nursed; leaving for Gibraltar the next day; Louise expecting Theo
  - Laura E. Cooke to Charles D. Barney 1872 Sep 30
    Gibraltar, Lake Erie, Ohio: [Jay Cooke] met them at Middle Bass with a tug; their daughter Dolly
- III. LETTERS TO CHARLES D. BARNEY AND LAURA E. COOKE, AND MISCELLANEOUS PAPERS
  - Cora H. Badger, Ogontz, to Charles D. Barney 1867 July 7
    Social; Sallie's [Cooke] 15th birthday
  - C. Lottie Blair, Troy, [ ? ], to Charles D. Barney 1864 Mar 24
    Ill with diptheria for several weeks; visit by Frank Porter who also went to the seminary to see Hannah and Emma Moss
  - C. Lottie Blair, Troy, [ ? ], to Charles D. Barney 1864 June 12
    Apparently to CDB while a soldier serving his country
  - John M. Butler, Philadelphia, Pennsylvania, to Charles D. Barney 1867 Sep 5
    Expresses congratulations on his engagement to Laura E. Cooke; praises characteristics of Laura and Charles; encourages him with the new position in Philadelphia, mentioning his qualities, experience and talent
  - Harry E. Cooke, Rome, Italy, to Laura E. Cooke 1869 Oct 17
    Visit to ruins, Caesar's Palace; offers a list of relics collected, along with each place of origin and an historical anecdote
  - Jay Cooke, Ogontz, to Charles D. Barney 1867 Aug 15
    Has arranged a position for him in their Philadelphia office, offering him "chances for gaining a perfect knowledge of [ ] kind of Banking" as well as future positions of trust, in order to aid him "in attaining a respectable & honorable standing..." for the sake of his daughter [Laura E. Cooke] and his friend [Charles D. Barney]
  - Jay Cooke, Jay Cooke & Company Bankers, to Charles D. Barney 1867 Aug 24
    Planning a discussion with his mother, Mrs. Barney, when in Sandusky, Ohio
  - Sallie E. Cooke, Ogontz, to Charles D. Barney 1867 July 7
    Re: her 15th birthday; social
  - Charles B. Dennis [uncle?], Office Mustering Department, 4 Army Corps, Chattanooga, Tennessee, to Charles D. Barney 1867 July 13
    Comments on [John Daniel] Imboden cutting up all sorts of capers down his way; news of Jay Smith and his return to the Army; report of William B. Rice from the front: Jay Butler well, Ed Pomeroy killed; Major or Lt. Col. B. B. McDonald, the "gopher" of Libby Prison, hated by the boys; Col. Kirby, commanding the Brigade, well-liked; Will Rice saw Brewer Smith who was well; Brigadier General Harker mortally wounded; General Davis division lost terribly; Jay Butler slightly wounded; a matter at Troy concerning Charles D. Barney; Charlie Hubbard dead; Captain Morrison having a brother [John Irwin Morrison (1806-1882), state treasurer of Indiana, 1865-1867] in the Treasury Department at Washington, D.C.
  - "Ma Barney" Keiffer, Chambersburg, Pennsylvania, to Charles D. Barney and Laura E. Cooke Barney 1869 Apr 25
    Met Frank at Harrisburg, Pennsylvania; judge Sloane Eade's conversation concerning the affairs of [Jay] Cooke, [William] Moorhead, John Butler, and Charles D. Barney; death of Mr. Culbertson; Mr. Keiffer going to country to preach; Sallie [Barney] going to Sabbath School with Frank
  - Broadside "Programme Drummer Boy!" at Norman Hall 1868 June 2, 3, 4
    B
  - Selected pages from Jay Cooke Private Banker by Henrietta M. Larson [HG2463.C6 L3] n.d.
- IV. LETTERS TO CHARLES McCLEW
  - Thomas Neilson, Glasgow, Scotland, to Charles McClew, Montgomery County, New York 1822 Jan 12
    Commenting on news of the recipients welfare and happiness and birth of a son and heir; eloquent letter expressing feelings of friendship and religious faith; attending second season of college in Glasgow; news of various family members and friends
  - Thomas Neilson, Glasgow, Scotland, to Charles McClew, Montgomery County, New York 1824 Mar 18
    Finishing the last of his classical curriculum at college and qualifying for the study of Divinity, hopefully at Paisley with Andrew Symington, the Cameronian Divinity professor; discourse on education, studies and student life; death of brother John's wife, leaving him with two babies; news of various family members and friends
  - Charles Neilson, Peter Hannay, and Elisabeth Hannay, Stranraer, Scotland, to Charles McClew, Montgomery County, New York 1827 July 1
    Circumstances of the death of Mary McGill's husband on April 28, 1887; news of national matters -- multitudes of banks failing in England; tremendous eclipse of manufacturing and trade, especially cotton and silk; failure of crops through Britain and Ireland
  - David McClew, Port Patrick, Scotland, to Charles McClew, Montgomery County, New York 1828 Mar 25
    Death of McClew's father-in-law; an old friend John being a wag at the John McThie Distillery of Whiskey; news of family and friends
  - Thomas Neilson, Rothesday, Scotland, to Charles McClew, Montgomery County, New York 1836 Apr 16
    Inquires of his brother Charles [Neilson] who sailed for New York last June and made no contact since; his family growing to four -- wife Alice and a daughter and a son; household also contains four boarders and [two] servants; news of various "Galloway relations"; comments on the agitation in Scotland in regard to civil establishments of religion; a meeting in Glasgow between their Synod and delegates from the Irish Synod concerning the "American Question!"
  - William and Mary McClew, Lennoxtown of Camphrey, Scotland, to Kilmarnock, Scotland 1840 Mar 24
    News of his own family, including sons William and Peter, daughters Jean and Mary, and of other family members and friends; death of John Nelson, and of his wife son William's wife, leaving one child; discussion of religious unrest in Scotland
- V. MISCELLANEOUS CORRESPONDENCE
  - Susan S. G. Pellet, Richmond, Virginia, to [Peter Joseph] Wagner, Washington, D.C. 1841 Feb 25
    Requests Mrs. Wagner to visit Richmond and discuss news of their mutual acquaintances from New York; Richmond being honored by a visit from the president-elect [William Henry Harrison (1773-1841)] and vice- president-elect [John Tyler (1790-1862)]; describes activities in honor of the president and vice-president and a sword presentation ceremony honoring the officers who are natives of Virginia, who had distinguished themselves during the last war; mentions [Thomas] Ritchie and Thomas Walker Gilmer, and meeting the president and vice-president at the governor's house
  - Frederick A. Culbert, Bloomingburgh, New York 1889 July 21
    Rowing and fishing, hunting, making a kite, boarding with Wilbur H. Brink
  - Alfred K[ean] Moe (1874- ), High School, Jersey City, New Jersey, to C. E. Hoffmann 1890 Jan 10
    In reply to his inquiry concerning his brother Paul who left them in the spring and reportedly was working as a mechanic in Brooklyn, New York; advises against hiring a detective, suggesting that he advertise in the newspapers of the large cities
  - C. E. Hoffman, Chicago, Illinois, to [Alfred K.] Moe 1890 Dec 28
    Concerning his brother Paul [written in German]
  - Unknown correspondent, Charlottesville, Virginia, to his parents 1904 Sep 21
    Relates the history of James B. Green, a blind man who tutors and [has served as a licentiate in the School of Law from 1896], and his wife; writes of Bettie Burwell Page Cocke (1841-1900), widow of John Bowdoin Cocke (1836-1889), and her daughter, Betty Page Cocke, who run the boarding house [on University Avenue next to St. Paul's Church] in which the correspondent boards; mentions "Raleigh," the African- American servant at the boarding house